Hi and welcome back. In this lesson we're going to be looking at type aliases and interfaces
in TypeScript. These two are very often confused, but they play very slightly different
rules. First of all, let's have a look at type aliases. Type alias lets us give a custom
name to a type. Think of it as a way to create your own shorthand for complex types.
Let's create a type of user ID. Now the user ID could be of type string or it could
be of type number. So kind of it's not a primitive, we're actually setting up as a complex
object, a complex type here, because it's got two of these types. So this user ID is
actually got two types string and number. And now what we can do is we can say let id1 is
of type user ID. We can set that as 101 and then we can have id2 and that is also of type
id. And that could be for example a123. So the user ID is basically a simple alias
for either type of string or number. Now instead of repeating the string number everywhere,
so instead of using it everywhere above our code, we can simply just refer to our user
id. And it looks much neater when we're actually writing the code for other developers
to understand. It could also be used for an aliases for objects. So let's have a look
as an example of that. So if we have to find a type of type user and the user has an
id of number and a name of type string and a flag of is admin, set to boolean. And then
we could create a user and say user 1. That is of type user. You can set the id to 1.
Set the name to Alice. And we can set the is admin flag to true. So this is acting
as a simple alias to this type of user. Now let's have a look at an a interface, the
difference. So an interface is primarily used to describe the shape of an object. It's
very similar to type aliases for objects, but it does come with some extra powers. So it's
best explained in an example. So let's have an interface of a user. And we can have the
same properties as before. So id of type number name type string and is admin of type
boolean. Now we're going to create an object or say user 2 of interface user. You can
just set the id property, then going to get a name, say bob. And then set the is admin
flag to false. So this pretty much looks the same as the alias example, but watch what
happens next. So interfaces can be extended to create new ones. And that's the difference
between this and its type alias. So we could do, for example, create an interface of employee,
now extends the user. And then we could add, for example, employee id and set that to a number.
Then we could create another user, say user 3. And that is of type employee this time.
You can set the name property to say charlie. But this time it's going to be complaining
because we need to specify id and is admin. So it's going to say id or maybe 4. And then
is admin. We're going to set to false. But also notice is now complaining because we
haven't specified the employee id. So we have to specify an additional property, employee
id and say 101. So this is the key difference between the interface and the type
alias is that the interfaces are also to extend the actual a previous interface. Whereas
a type alias does not. This is perfect for being able to do objects inheritance in a
type script. So let's have a look at a further examples just to illustrate this. So let's
say we have an interface of type animal. And this species, we're going to set the type
string. And then we're going to create another interface of dog that extends the interface
for animal. And we're going to provide a method of bark. So on this interface, we're
creating a method that's going to be overridden when we supply it, when we're actually
construct the object. So let's now do an example with type aliases instead. So we're
going to create a type, and let's say the type of animal type. And this has a property
of species of type string. Then we can create a type of dog type, which is a combination
of animal type. And it has a method called bark, which is a avoid method. So look at
the different string sex between doing this. So this is like a combined type, where this
is probably much neater in effect is much clearer, where we can actually extend it. Let's
still have a look at another example, because interfaces can also be reopens and merged,
whereas type aliases cannot. So let's create an interface called car. And this has a make
property of type string. And then we're going to have another interface. And look at
this, we're going to also call it car. But this has a property called model of type string.
And this looks quite strange, right? Now what we can do is we can create a natural instance
of my car of a de actual interface of car. And then we can combine the two together. So
if we hover this, we can specify the make of say Toyota. I could spell it to Toyota. But
the TypeScript has also telling us we need to also supply the model is combining both of these
two interfaces together, because they've got the same name. So we can come in here and then
say model and say gorilla. And now TypeScript is happy. If we try to do the same thing
of a type aliases, then TypeScript will go absolutely crazy. It's not allowed to do that.
If we try to do the same thing and merge with the type aliases, it's going to cause an error.
So in summary, we should use type aliases when we want to, for example, to unions or
primitives or tuples, whereas interfaces should be used when we want to describe the object
shapes. And we also want to benefit from extension and emerging abilities.